<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-23T12:36:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">the-strays-blog</title><subtitle>The home of John Mathena&apos;s stray throughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Bear Shows Us How To Grow</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/10/the-bear-shows-us-how-to-grow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bear Shows Us How To Grow" /><published>2023-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/10/the-bear-shows-us-how-to-grow</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/10/the-bear-shows-us-how-to-grow.html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Minor spoilers for The Bear season 2 lie ahead&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Episode four of season two of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bear_(TV_series)#Season_2_(2023)&quot;&gt;The Bear&lt;/a&gt; takes a slight detour from a Chicago family restaurant aiming to reinvent itself to a high-end kitchen in the Netherlands. The Chicago shop’s head chefs send their baker, Marcus, to Copenhagen to learn some new dishes from a pastry chef named Luca.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bright and early just before 5 am after crossing an ocean, Marcus meets Luca in the kitchen and hits the ground running. The show immediately portrays Luca as a prototypical upscale chef; straight to the point in his instructions with high expectations. But what surprises me as Marcus continues to train under him is his patience and calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Marcus is no slouch. Last season, he established himself as one of the most creative and hardworking talents in the restaurant. He kept meticulous notes and drawings of pastry ideas in his journal while stocking the whole kitchen with loaves of bread and rolls needed for their homestyle dishes. He’s demonstrated he’s more than capable of excelling in the hyper-competitive dining industry. But just because it’s clear you have what it takes doesn’t mean anyone - especially a person with power, experience to share, or both - will give you the time and space it takes to realize your potential. And yet Luca does!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He never yells at Marcus when he stumbles. He doesn’t accost him with petty or offensive insults and slurs like JK Simmons in Whiplash. He’s stern and consistent while also kind and helpful (and a bit goofy). Finally the two open up to each other in one of my favorite scenes of television in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They ask each other how they found themselves cutting and weighing chunks of raw dough together at 5 in the morning. Luca shares that he ended up as a dishwasher for misbehaving when he was young and fell in love with working in kitchens. He never looked back and he always felt like he was the best wherever he went, until he got a job with this other young chef. It’s heavily implied that this other young chef is Carmy (arguably the main character of the show and head of the restaurant back in Chicago) but I digress. Luca admits this other chef was the best he’d ever seen. Better than Luca could ever hope to be. And Luca ultimately decided the best thing he could do for himself was try to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And did you get better?” Marcus asks.&lt;br /&gt;
“Better than I ever thought I could be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m paraphrasing here because I’m too lazy to look up the actual quote. Marcus then jokingly refers to Luca as the Scotty Pippen to this chef’s Michael Jordan. “Still a hall of famer!” Marcus’ path to the kitchen also took some twists and turns. He was a D3 college football player and eventually found his way into kitchens needing to make money to support his sick mother. He started at a McDonald’s and ended up at his current restaurant because he was in there for lunch a lot and the previous owner wanted to open a bakery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I adored watching a black man from Chicago live out his dreams. Marcus went on a whole journey centered on him and his quest to hone his craft and find his beauty. It was joyful. We don’t see enough of it. This episode serves as a blueprint and proof-of-concept for TV to give us more character journeys like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love that this episode shows us how driven, highly skilled people can achieve and learn so much from each other without the bitterness and vitriol we’re bred to believe needs to be part of the process. We don’t have to tear each other down to build ourselves up. We don’t have to sabotage those who are or may become better than us at one time or another. We all learn and grow best when we give others the space, time, and tools they need to make the best of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John Mathena</name></author><summary type="html">(Minor spoilers for The Bear season 2 lie ahead)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Please Don’t Make Me Kill</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/Please-don't-make-me-kill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Please Don’t Make Me Kill" /><published>2022-04-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/Please-don&apos;t-make-me-kill</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/14/Please-don&apos;t-make-me-kill.html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/student-debt-relief-payment-pause-free-colege-military-navy-recruitment-education-11649800856&quot;&gt;WSJ op-ed&lt;/a&gt; made
its rounds through my little corner of lefty twitter. I’m not a subscriber, so I did not read it. 
Take this post with however big a grain of salt you feel appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The op-ed title and subtitle read: 
“&lt;strong&gt;An Unintended Consequence of Student-Debt Relief&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Will young Americans volunteer for the armed forces in adequate numbers?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty disappointed Chrome incognito mode couldn’t bust me into this article. I considered many career paths in and around the US Military to 
help pay off my student loan debt. I’m curious exactly how common a path this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My immediate guess is: pretty common. Americans valorize going into military or police service. 
College students probably see loan forgiveness on top of additional respect as a win-win. I certainly did. 
But after working in and around Intel and Law Enforcement, I realized two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a terrible career path for me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I convinced myself to want this career path because of the social benefits and the loan forgiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number one deserves its own posts - or series, and I’m certainly not the first person to critique the US Military -  but two I can get into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both my parents are lifelong public servants (my dad a civil engineer and my mom a journalist, teacher, and now principal). 
I grew up dreaming of serving my community. I did well in language classes through grade school and had an ‘analytical’ mind. 
Post 9/11, young nerds who loved languages and wanted to serve found a very well lit path to Uncle Sam’s HR department. 
But there are lots of jobs where you serve your people and don’t involve volunteering to kill or be killed (or support those that do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of those jobs pay shit (read: teaching, social work, nursing…and many many many more). 
And many don’t carry the glorious weight of having ‘served’, though many damn well should. 
I’m not bashing individual cops or soldiers. I’ve worked with many and many earnestly try to do good work. 
But without going into number one, as I said I wouldn’t, both jobs require you be ready to end another person’s life as part of your job. 
That’s a serious fucking act. 
And we should not be lamenting this country taking a baby step in creating a more just education system because 
some kids might not be pushed toward killing in order to finance their schooling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John Mathena</name></author><summary type="html">A WSJ op-ed made its rounds through my little corner of lefty twitter. I’m not a subscriber, so I did not read it. Take this post with however big a grain of salt you feel appropriate.</summary></entry></feed>